<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Caffeinated Coding]]></title>
  <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-27T14:36:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Earl St Sauver]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Rest from Running]]></title>
    <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/22/taking-a-rest-from-running/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T20:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/22/taking-a-rest-from-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a week ago, I got to prove the "it's like riding a bike!" saying wrong by completely forgetting how to ride a bike. Maybe more accurately, I found out that some bikes use a backpedaling to engage the breaks. I also learned quite effectively that awkwardly trying to break as you're about to make a turn is not the time to do an equipment check. Fortunately the cars around me all stopped, stopping to watch the spectacle.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p> Like any 5-6 year old learning to ride a bike, in the middle of the street, surrounded by commuters trying to figure out what the hell the awkward looking college student is doing, I fell off my bike in the middle of the street, right in front of the main building I take classes in. I took a decent chunk of skin off my knee and dinged up my hands and an ankle, but I was at least able to get the bike locked up.</p>

<p>Now fortunately the office people at our building are absolutely fantastic and they had gauze and antibacterial goop, but I might have initially underestimated the severity of the rather decent chunk of skin I took off my leg as a professor said "Oh my gawd!" The gauze took care of things initially, including survivng a five mile run into harvard and back, but two days later it was looking weird and so I went to our health services. They decided that it should get a "Tegaderm" dressing that's better. I asked about it and what it is, and they just answered something about "It's a protein... it's like a second skin." Not wanting to push it, I settled down and realized that this was definitely the first time I'd encountered technology that was sufficiently advanced it was indistinguishable from magic. I asked if I could go running with it and the super friendly nurse said "oh, you should be fine as long as it doesn't come off." I of course went running the next day, and the whole thing was coming off by the end of the night, although I did set a Mile PR of 6:54.</p>

<p>The next day I went back to Health Services and they admonished me universally for running with the leg dressing on. The waiting room was surprisingly full of people who appeared to have made rather poor friday night life decisions. When I got into an examining room the nurse practitioner and a doctor walking by both admonished me for runnign with the dressing on. I was a little confused as I'd asked <em>multiple</em> times. Despite the empirical evidence that I can, in fact, run quite fine with their weird dressing on, I think I ought to stick to the opinion of the saturday morning crew. From what I can tell, they've really seen some things in their time.</p>

<p>But now I'm on a running hiatus for at minimum the next week, which is a really weird experience for me. I've only been running regularly for about two years, and I only got back into the habbit of running ~5 times/week about 6 months ago, but it's definitely become a part of my day that I look forward to more than most. The feeling about 3 miles in where I really hit my stride is about as good as a peanut butter ice cream blend. I don't say that about many things.</p>

<p>I think the biggest thing that I worry about is that once I stop I won't start again. I've lost about 70 pounds over the last 3 years and the biggest problem I've definitely had with running is making it still work into my schedule and fighting for it to have a place in my life. It's so easy to push running out of my life and let work or relationships take its place. I just find something missing from my life when running's gone though. It's the same feeling of success and when a piece of code just works, except very seldom does running crash with no explanation. I spend some time each week reading about running and lifting weights, but when I hit the pavement it's just pure mechanical and chemical energy flowing out of me. I can feel myself, Earl the animal, a breathing, seating, agglomerate of things meant purely for this purpose. The parts of myself that make up Earl-the-man, the rational and perceptive are still there, but they're laying in the background. I guess I'm torn between feeling like running has become something I'm dependent on my life and a crucial piece of balance in it.</p>

<p>Realistically, it's probably both balance and addiction at the same time. Being corporeal has a cost, I suppose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
