<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Caffeinated Coding]]></title>
  <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-22T21:28:47-04:00</updated>
  <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Earl St Sauver]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Rest from Running]]></title>
    <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/22/taking-a-rest-from-running/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T20:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/22/taking-a-rest-from-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a week ago, I got to prove the &#8220;it&#8217;s like riding a bike!&#8221; saying wrong by completely forgetting how to ride a bike. Maybe more accurately, I found out that some bikes use a backpedaling to engage the breaks. I also learned quite effectively that awkwardly trying to break as you&#8217;re about to make a turn is not the time to do an equipment check. Fortunately the cars around me all stopped, stopping to watch the spectacle.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p> Like any 5-6 year old learning to ride a bike, in the middle of the street, surrounded by commuters trying to figure out what the hell the awkward looking college student is doing, I fell off my bike in the middle of the street, right in front of the main building I take classes in. I took a decent chunk of skin off my knee and dinged up my hands and an ankle, but I was at least able to get the bike locked up.</p>

<p>Now fortunately the office people at our building are absolutely fantastic and they had gauze and antibacterial goop, but I might have initially underestimated the severity of the rather decent chunk of skin I took off my leg as a professor said &#8220;Oh my gawd!&#8221; The gauze took care of things initially, including survivng a five mile run into harvard and back, but two days later it was looking weird and so I went to our health services. They decided that it should get a &#8220;Tegaderm&#8221; dressing that&#8217;s better. I asked about it and what it is, and they just answered something about &#8220;It&#8217;s a protein&#8230; it&#8217;s like a second skin.&#8221; Not wanting to push it, I settled down and realized that this was definitely the first time I&#8217;d encountered technology that was sufficiently advanced it was indistinguishable from magic. I asked if I could go running with it and the super friendly nurse said &#8220;oh, you should be fine as long as it doesn&#8217;t come off.&#8221; I of course went running the next day, and the whole thing was coming off by the end of the night, although I did set a Mile PR of 6:54.</p>

<p>The next day I went back to Health Services and they admonished me universally for running with the leg dressing on. The waiting room was surprisingly full of people who appeared to have made rather poor friday night life decisions. When I got into an examining room the nurse practitioner and a doctor walking by both admonished me for runnign with the dressing on. I was a little confused as I&#8217;d asked <em>multiple</em> times. Despite the empirical evidence that I can, in fact, run quite fine with their weird dressing on, I think I ought to stick to the opinion of the saturday morning crew. From what I can tell, they&#8217;ve really seen some things in their time.</p>

<p>But now I&#8217;m on a running hiatus for at minimum the next week, which is a really weird experience for me. I&#8217;ve only been running regularly for about two years, and I only got back into the habbit of running ~5 times/week about 6 months ago, but it&#8217;s definitely become a part of my day that I look forward to more than most. The feeling about 3 miles in where I really hit my stride is about as good as a peanut butter ice cream blend. I don&#8217;t say that about many things.</p>

<p>I think the biggest thing that I worry about is that once I stop I won&#8217;t start again. I&#8217;ve lost about 70 pounds over the last 3 years and the biggest problem I&#8217;ve definitely had with running is making it still work into my schedule and fighting for it to have a place in my life. It&#8217;s so easy to push running out of my life and let work or relationships take its place. I just find something missing from my life when running&#8217;s gone though. It&#8217;s the same feeling of success and when a piece of code just works, except very seldom does running crash with no explanation. I spend some time each week reading about running and lifting weights, but when I hit the pavement it&#8217;s just pure mechanical and chemical energy flowing out of me. I can feel myself, Earl the animal, a breathing, seating, agglomerate of things meant purely for this purpose. The parts of myself that make up Earl-the-man, the rational and perceptive are still there, but they&#8217;re laying in the background. I guess I&#8217;m torn between feeling like running has become something I&#8217;m dependent on my life and a crucial piece of balance in it.</p>

<p>Realistically, it&#8217;s probably both balance and addiction at the same time. Being corporeal has a cost, I suppose.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spotter Beta Testers Wanted]]></title>
    <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/21/spotter-beta-testers-wanted/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-21T17:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/21/spotter-beta-testers-wanted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With an Apple Developer account in hand, the Spotter project is off to a rocking start. I&#8217;d really love to start getting some user feedback for the app, even before it hits full functionality. The beta signup link is here [http://tflig.ht/QnqkjJ(http://tflig.ht/QnqkjJ). The wifi logging only happens when the application is currently open so the usefulness is inherently limited. The application should ideally run in the background for a long period of time until it&#8217;s disabled by the user.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>However, that refactoring is going to have to wait for next weeks build. Spotter&#8217;s almost certainly going to need to collect another set of information (type of iphone, carrier, proximity-sensor information) so this data set will likely just be used for development. Spotter also doesn&#8217;t yet annotate the google map with the location of a network drop, it just centers the map. Trust that when the map moves, things are happening in the application.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://i.imgur.com/otZ2E.png" width="320" height="480" title="Spotter Screenshot" ></p>

<p>I feel like every time I open Xcode I learn how to do a half dozen things. I don&#8217;t know if that means I&#8217;m a quick learner or if that means I&#8217;m still a mediocre Objective-C programmer, but it&#8217;s nice to feel that constant rush of problem solving and learning. I think that might be the thing that has me come back to programming again and again is that I always feel like I&#8217;m really learning every time I sit down at the keyboard.</p>

<p>For example, the use of the delegate pattern everywhere throughout the app doesn&#8217;t feel natural to me. It seems to add a degree of complexity almost inherently to the application by abstracting how messages are passed through the application. I think that might be one of the downsides to entering the programming world through the relatively nice playing world of python and ruby. I&#8217;m going in the &#8220;harder&#8221; programming language direction, which means learning is an uphil battle. People who learned to program in C, they&#8217;ve seen things. They&#8217;re the Bane&#8217;s of the programming world, &#8220;they&#8217;re born in darkness&#8221;.</p>

<h3>Backend Work</h3>

<p>I&#8217;ve now started design on the first chunk of data processing scripts. It almost immediately became clear that this stage will influence the type of data which we need in at least a few ways. First of all, once a suitable size of data has been collected, the collection of network data can switch from a background always on process to only checking &#8220;regions of interest&#8221; in the background. Once there&#8217;s sufficient data collected it&#8217;ll be possible to divide the data collection into two pieces. <strong>First</strong>  , The data collection done by the library as the library is actively running and monitoring network drops. <strong>Second</strong>, A set of coordinate regions that are <em>of interest</em> to the database which the phone can turn on, take a couple measurements for, and then turn back off.</p>

<p>This will allow for smart collection of data. Once it becomes clear where the generally problematic areas in a region are, there&#8217;s no reason to continually poll the phone to determine that there is, for instance, most definitively a dead zone at the enterance to the subway. We can limit the background polling to &#8220;interesting areas&#8221; where we get conflicting data.</p>

<h3>Apple Store Guidelines</h3>

<p>I am at least a little curious whether this project will be pushing up against the limits of what the iPhone can do in an authorized background process. For those who aren&#8217;t aware, typically there are 3 classes of location services that a phone can use. First, there are foreground services that run only when the application is open and running. This is the kind of locations ervice that&#8217;s currently used. Second there are services which receive updates only when there&#8217;s a &#8220;substantial change&#8221; in the application&#8217;s location. This isn&#8217;t particularly helpful as the phone determines there&#8217;s been a significant change in location when it switches to a new cell tower. However this location information is far too coarsely grained to be useful. The third type of background service is a always running background service. These are incredibly restricted, and I&#8217;m unclear if the application will qualify as being a &#8220;real time location&#8221; application. While spotter is fundamentally a geographic logging application, and there&#8217;s certainly some precedent to allow applications of a similar sort to use the background processes indefinitely, it makes me nervous.</p>

<p>Currently, at least one application is using background location processes for real time monitoring of locatin. <a href="http://runkeeper.com/home">RunKeeper</a> has a wonderful application that lets you use GPS logging to follow your runs as you go on them. I&#8217;m just not clear if they had to do some extra work to reclassify the background process as a different type (a finite length background service, that calls more finite background services or something of the sort).</p>

<p>If nothing else, I hope that they&#8217;ll grant Spotter some leniancy as it&#8217;s a research project. If they were to turn down the application, I believe that it would still be possible to obtain an enterprise distribution license and distribute it to a limited audience here. That would be unfortunate, but I think it still might be possible to then license this technology out to other universities and hope that they implement the project in a similar way.</p>

<p>~Earl</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Plus: Surprisingly Satisfing]]></title>
    <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/18/google-plus-im-surprisingly-satisfied/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T22:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/18/google-plus-im-surprisingly-satisfied</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I opened Google+ yesterday and I was actually somewhat astonished by how <em>good</em> it just is. I didn&#8217;t expect it to be still actively improving after the soaring hopes and dashed expectations that acompanied the Google+ launch, but in the interim the Google+ team has substantailly improved the product. I think it will definitely gain traction over the next few years, and while it won&#8217;t probably eclipse facebook, I think it&#8217;ll gain market share over the next few years.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I think that the experience of Google+ is notably better than facebook in at least a few ways.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The separation of content into streams is much more natural. Facebook still seems to drump everything that&#8217;s <em>social</em> into one gigantic vat of streaming content that I have to sort through to find information from people that I actually care about. Even being incredibly vindictive with the &#8220;Hide posts from&#8221; feature in facebook has still not managed to sort out the crap-a-lanche that is my newsfeed.</p>

<p>Google Plus&#8217;s circles concept is really actually incredibly brilliant because it lets me change social contexts easily. When I&#8217;m home visitng family for a few weeks I can easily change the people that I&#8217;m interested in hearing about by just changing my circles setting.</p></li>
<li><p>Google Chat/Hangouts are how I want to do my realtime communication with anyone, anywhere. With virtually everyone under the age of 30 on gmail at this point, it makes chatting incredibly easy and extensive. Hangouts are how I&#8217;d like all of my remote meetings to be done in the future. I can easily add a whiteboard, talk with multiple people, and send files related to the chat. It&#8217;s really the holy grail of consumer grade videoconfrencing as far as I can tell.</p>

<p>The problem with the facebook chat model is that it still doesn&#8217;t to my knowledge, show everyone who is online and available as available for chat. It also complicates things by having &#8220;mobile&#8221; facebooking be sometimes online, sometimes marked as mobile, and sometimes offline. When I send a facebook caht to someone, I don&#8217;t know whether or not they&#8217;re reading it now or whether they&#8217;ll read it in a week when they next log in. That makes it virtually useless to me.</p></li>
<li><p>The Google-sphere has not been corrupted by a thousand farmvilles and social reading apps. When I click on a link in Google+, I almost invariably get taken directly to whatever newspaper article was being linked to. That in and of itself is worth enough to make me reconsider.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>All in all, I think I will make a conscious effort to continue to use Google+ for a while. I really think it&#8217;s the solution that can and should win out in the long run. I just hope Google has the long range vision to continue to put the effort to keep up its development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spotter is now in development]]></title>
    <link href="estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/18/spotter-is-now-in-development/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T17:28:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>estsauver.herokuapp.com/blog/2012/09/18/spotter-is-now-in-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a smart phone user, there are very few things that are still really frustrating. By and large, the operating systems for most major smartphones are, at this point, polished incredibly well. However, the process of switching between wifi and cellular network coverage is still mistifyingly bad. As the phone loses wifi strength, the transmission of data becomes increasingly less reliable on the poor network, but there&#8217;s no attempt made to establish a cellular connection.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It&#8217;s like my phone is absolutely startled that I walk around with it while accessing data. It always seems to act like nothing of this sort had ever happenned before.</p>

<p>I think this can be fixed by using empirical models of where connections are dropped to perdict regions where wifi is likely to fail around a cell phone user. Using this information, I want to create a library that will allow application developers to take predictive action when their users are about to enter rough internet seas.</p>

<p>I think this project will take roughly three phases.</p>

<ol>
<li><h3>Aquire data for as many network/wifi transitions as possible to model where these transitions occur.</h3>

<p> As of the writing, it&#8217;s unclear what the uncertainty for this transition is, when the effective wifi transmission stops, and when the cell network is switched over to. We&#8217;d like to have enough data, if only for a relatively small geographic area initially, that we can effectively model the wireless characteristics of a pilot area.</p></li>
<li><h3>Model the pilot area to generate regions of likely network failure.</h3>

<p> In order for the data to be meaningfully used, it needs to be converted from a large series of points to a set of regions where connection failure is likely. Performing this server side asynchronously seems to be the only reasonable choice that doesn&#8217;t destroy battery life. This step will also involve the deployment of a backend capable of repsonding to latitude longitude pairs with sets of regions.</p></li>
<li><h3>Deploy a library which responds to the set of regions and takes meaningful action to minimize disruption.</h3>

<p> Without the ability to use this data in real time, the data is really only useful to IT people trying to see where their network is covered. We&#8217;d like to develop a library that will begin cacheing in advance when nearing a poor service area and will reduce cacheing in a good service area. I&#8217;d like to implement switching from wifi to WWAN programaticaly, but that&#8217;s likely impossible without the cooperation of the phone providers.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Spotter is currently part of the way through the first step. The project is working on the simulator, but it&#8217;s not yet tested on an actual iPhone, pending an Apple developer license. With some luck, we can begin limited beta testing of the client by the end of the month.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m currently set up to use <a href="www.parse.com">Parse.com</a> as the backend for this project, but this could change as the project scales. Parse has the immense bennefit of providing an easy to use cross platform library allowing us to potentially extend this project to other device types as time goes forward. I&#8217;m quite open to hearing other possible alternatives, but it certainly seems like Parse is the best solution for now.</p>

<p>Questions/comments? Please log an issue on our github <a href="https://github.com/estsauver/spotter">https://github.com/estsauver/spotter</a>, I&#8217;d love to hear from you. If you don&#8217;t have to</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
